in your tree, because we are all connected, and 75 million may seem like a lot, but in a few years, it's quite likely we will have a family tree with all, almost all, seven billion people on Earth. But does it really matter? What's the importance? And I do think it is important, and I'll give you five reasons why, really quickly. First, it's got scientific value. This is an unprecedented history of the human race, and it's giving us valuable data about how diseases are inherited, how people migrate, and there's a team of scientists at MIT right now studying the world family tree. Number two, it brings history alive. I found out I'm connected to Albert Einstein, so I told my seven-year-old son that,
en su árbol, porque todos estamos conectados, y 75 millones pueden parecer mucho, pero en pocos años, es muy probable que tengamos un árbol genealógico con todos, o casi todas, las 7 mil millones de personas en la Tierra. Pero ¿realmente importa? ¿Cuál es la importancia? Yo creo que es importante, y les voy a dar 5 razones muy rápidamente. En primer lugar, tiene valor científico. Esta es una historia sin precedentes de la raza humana, y nos está dando datos valiosos acerca de cómo se heredan las enfermedades, cómo la gente emigra y hay un equipo de científicos del MIT ahora estudiando el árbol genealógico mundial. Número dos, le da vida a la historia. Me enteré de que estoy conectado a Albert Einstein, así que se lo dije a mi hijo de 7 años de edad,
and he was totally engaged. Now Albert Einstein is not some dead white guy with weird hair. He's Uncle Albert. (Laughter) And my son wanted to know, "What did he say? What is E = MC squared?" Also, it's not all good news. I found a link to Jeffrey Dahmer, the serial killer, but I will say that's on my wife's side. (Laughter) (Applause) So I want to make that clear. Sorry, honey. Number three, interconnectedness. We all come from the same ancestor, and you don't have to believe the literal Bible version, but scientists talk about Y chromosomal Adam and mitochondrial Eve, and these were about 100,000 to 300,000 years ago. We all have a bit of their DNA in us. They are our great-great-great-great-great-great -- continue that for about 7,000 times -- grandparents, and so that means we literally all are biological cousins as well, and estimates vary, but probably the farthest cousin you have on Earth is about a 50th cousin. Now, it's not just ancestors we share, descendants. If you have kids, and they have kids, look how quickly the descendants accumulate. So in 10, 12 generations, you're going to have thousands of offspring, and millions of offspring. Number four, a kinder world. Now, I know that there are family feuds. I have three sons, so I see how they fight. But I think that there's also a human bias to treat your family a little better than strangers. I think this tree is going to be bad news for bigots, because they're going to have to realize that they are cousins with thousands of people in whatever ethnic group they happen to have issues with, and I think you look back at history, and a lot of the terrible things we've done to each other is because one group thinks another group is sub-human, and you can't do that anymore. We're not just part of the same species. We're part of the same family. We share 99.9 percent of our DNA. Now the final one is number five, a democratizing effect. Some genealogy has an elitist strain, like people say, "Oh, I'm descended from Mary Queen of Scots and you're not, so you cannot join my country club." But that's really going to be hard to do now, because everyone is related. I'm descended from Mary Queen of Scots -- by marriage, but still. So it's really a fascinating time in the history of family, because it's changing so fast. There is gay marriage and sperm donors and there's intermarriage on an unprecedented scale, and this makes some of my more conservative cousins a little nervous, but I actually think it's a good thing. I think the more inclusive the idea of family is, the better, because then you have more potential caretakers, and as my aunt's eighth cousin twice removed Hillary Clinton says -- (Laughter) — it takes a village. So I have all these hundreds and thousands, millions of new cousins. I thought, what can I do with this information? And that's when I decided, why not throw a party? So that's what I'm doing. And you're all invited. Next year, next summer, I will be hosting what I hope is the biggest and best family reunion in history. (Applause) Thank you. I want you there. I want you there. It's going to be at the New York Hall of Science, which is a great venue, but it's also on the site of the former World's Fair, which is, I think, very appropriate, because I see this as a family reunion meets a world's fair. There's going to be exhibits and food, music. Paul McCartney is 11 steps away, so I'm hoping he brings his guitar. He hasn't RSVP'd yet, but fingers crossed. And there is going to be a day of speakers, of fascinating cousins. It's early, but I've already, I've got some lined up. Cass Sunstein, my cousin who is perhaps the most brilliant legal scholar, will be talking. He was a former member of the Obama administration. And on the other side of the political spectrum, George H.W. Bush, number 41, the father, he has agreed to participate, and Nick Kroll, the comedian, and Dr. Oz, and many more to come. And, of course, the most important is that you, I want you guys there, and I invite you to go to GlobalFamilyReunion.org and figure out how you're on the family tree, because these are big issues, family and tribe, and I don't know all the answers, but I have a lot of smart relatives, including you guys, so together, I think we can figure it out. Only together can we solve these big problems. So from cousin to cousin, I thank you. I can't wait to see you. Goodbye. (Applause)
y él estaba totalmente cautivado. Ahora Albert Einstein no es un hombre blanco muerto con el pelo raro. Es el tío Albert. (Risas) Y mi hijo quería saber, "¿Qué ha dicho? ¿Qué es E = MC²?" Además, no todo son buenas noticias. Me encontré con un enlace a Jeffrey Dahmer, el asesino en serie, pero he de decir que viene del lado de mi esposa. (Risas) (Aplausos) Así que quiero que esto quede claro. Lo siento, cariño. Número tres, la interconexión. Todos venimos de un mismo ancestro, y uno no tiene que creer en la versión literal de la Biblia, pero los científicos hablan del Y cromosomal de Adán y la Eva mitocondrial, y estos fueron hace unos 100 000 a 300 000 años. Todos tenemos un poco de su ADN en nosotros. Ellos son nuestra tatara-tatara- tatara-tatara-tatara-tatara —seguir que por cerca de 7000 veces— abuelos, y lo que significa, literalmente, es que todos somos primos biológicos también, y las estimaciones varían, pero probablemente el primo más lejano que tienen en la Tierra se trata de un primo 50° Ahora, no es sólo que compartimos ancestros, descendientes. Si tienen niños, y ellos tienen hijos, miren cómo rápidamente los descendientes se acumulan. Así que en 10, 12 generaciones, Uds. van a tener miles de descendientes, y millones de descendientes. Número cuatro, un mundo más amable. Ahora, sé que hay disputas familiares. Tengo 3 hijos, así que veo cómo se pelean. Pero creo que también qe hay un sesgo humano a tratar a su familia un poco mejor que a los extranjeros. Creo que este árbol va a ser una mala noticia para los fanáticos, porque van a tener que darse cuenta de que son primos de miles de personas en cualquier grupo étnico con el que tengan problemas, y creo que uno mira hacia atrás en la historia, y un montón de las terribles cosas que nos hemos hecho el uno al otro se debe a que un grupo cree que otro grupo es sub-humano, y uno no puede hacer eso ya más. No somos solo una parte de la misma especie, somos parte de la misma familia. Compartimos el 99,9 % de nuestro ADN. Ahora la final es la número cinco, un efecto democratizador. Para algunos la genealogía tiene una cepa elitista, como dice la gente, "Oh, yo soy descendiente de María, reina de Escocia y tú no, así que no puedes ingresar a mi club social". Pero eso va a ser realmente difícil de hacer ahora, porque todo el mundo está relacionado. Yo soy descendiente de María reina de Escocia, por matrimonio, pero aún así. Así que es realmente un momento fascinante en la historia de la familia, porque está cambiando tan rápido. Hay matrimonios gay y donantes de semen y hay matrimonios mixtos en una escala sin precedentes, y esto pone a algunos de mis primos más conservadores un poco nerviosos, pero realmente creo que es una buena cosa. Creo que cuanto más inclusiva es la idea de familia, mejor, porque entonces uno tiene más cuidadores potenciales, y como la prima octava mi dos veces tía lejana Hillary Clinton dice —(risas)— se necesita un pueblo. Así que tengo todos estos cientos y miles, millones de nuevos primos. Pensé, ¿qué puedo hacer con esta información? Y fue entonces cuando me decidí, ¿por qué no hacer una fiesta? Así que eso es l o que estoy haciendo. Y están todos invitados. El año que viene, el próximo verano, Seré el anfitrión de lo que espero sea la reunión de la familia más grande y mejor de la historia. (Aplausos) Gracias. Los quiero allí. Los quiero allí. Será en el New York Hall of Science, que es una gran sede, pero también es el sitio de la antigua Feria Mundial, que es, creo, muy apropiado, porque veo esto como una reunión familiar se reúne una feria mundial. Habrá exposiciones y comida y música. Paul McCartney está a 11 pasos de distancia, así que espero que él traiga su guitarra. Él no ha respondido todavía, pero cruzo los dedos. Y no va a ser un día de discursos, de primos fascinantes. Es temprano, pero estoy listo, tengo algunos alineados. Cass Sunstein, mi primo que es quizás el jurista más brillante, hablará. Fue miembro de la administración Obama. Y en el otro lado del espectro político, George H.W. Bush, el número 41, el padre, que ha aceptado participar, y Nick Kroll, el cómico, y el Dr. Oz, y muchos más por venir. Y, por supuesto, los más importantes que son Uds. Los quiero allá, y los invito a ir a GlobalFamilyReunion.org y averiguar cómo están en el árbol de familia, debido a que estos son temas importantes, familia y tribu, y no sé todas las respuestas, pero tengo un montón de parientes inteligentes, incluidos Uds., así que juntos, creo que podemos averiguarlo. Solo juntos podemos resolver estos grandes problemas. Así que de primo a primo, les doy las gracias. No puedo esperar a verte. Adiós. (Aplausos)